{"tossups": [{"question": "British philosopher G.E. Moore wrote a famous \"defense of\" this phrase that inspired his later \"Proof of an External World.\" This phrase titles a pamphlet that argues it is absurd for an island to rule a continent and which advocates for replacing the Magna Carta with a Continental Charter. For ten points, give this two word phrase that titles a Thomas Paine pamphlet advocating for American independence, a term which indicates obviously correct beliefs.", "answer": "<b><u>Common Sense</u></b> (accept \"A Defence of <b><u>Common Sense</u></b>\")", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A commission made up of, in part, Founding Father Gouverneur Morris drew the plans for this city between the modern streets of Houston and 115th. The Stonewall Inn Riots of the late 1960s occurred in this island's Greenwich Village. The Director of the New Netherlands Peter Minuit supposedly bought this U.S. island for twenty-two dollars worth of beads and other trading goods. For ten points, name this island, the most densely populated New York City borough.", "answer": "<b><u>Manhattan</u></b> (or <b><u>Manhattan</u></b> Island; prompt on \"New York\", \"New York City\", or \"New York County\"; prompt on \"The City\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This period began after Visigothic nobleman Pelayo [[peh-LY-oh]] rebelled against Governor Munuza, establishing the Kingdom of Asturias. Large<em> parias</em> tributes were paid during this period, which began with the Battle of Covadonga. This period included a victory over the Almohads at Las Navas de Tolosa, and this period ended with the conquest of Granada by the Catholic monarchs of Castile and Aragon. For ten points, name this period in which the Iberian peninsula was \"reclaimed\" from Muslim kingdoms.", "answer": "<b><u>Reconquista</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A play in this genre depicts the general Cleon as a slave to Demos, whose affections are vied for by a sausage-seller named Agoracritus [[ah-gor-AH-krih-tus]]. Menander [[meh-NAN-der]] worked in the \"Athenian New\" school of this genre, whereas its \"Old\" form is seen in plays like<em> The Knights</em> and<em> The Clouds</em> by Aristophanes, who made fun of Socrates. For ten points, name this lighthearted and often satirical ancient Greek genre of plays, contrasted with Tragedy.", "answer": "<b><u>Comedy</u></b> (accept Ancient Greek <b><u>Comedy</u></b>; or Athenian <b><u>Comedy</u></b>; accept Old, Middle, or New <b><u>Comedy</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "In 1992, this modern nation invaded its eastern neighbor in an attempt to protect the independence of the region of Nagorno-Karabakh. Talaat Pasha ordered forced marches through the Syrian Desert by this nation's namesake ethnic group, killing over one million of them. Multiple wars with Azerbaijan have been fought by, for ten points, what Caucasian nation that faced a 20th century \"Genocide\" under the Ottoman Empire?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Armenia</u></b> (or <b><u>Hayastan</u></b>i Hanrapetut\u2019yun; accept <b><u>Armenia</u></b>n Soviet Socialist Republic; or <b><u>Haykakan</u></b> Sovetakan Soc'ialistakan Hanrapetut'yun; accept <b><u>Armenia</u></b>n Genocide)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Along with acting as watchmen, freedmen known as<em> vigiles</em> [[VIH-jih-less]] worked in this profession, often using a substance called<em> acetum</em> [[AH-keh-tum]]. Men in this profession in Ancient Greece used ox intestines as a flexible hose. The first brigade of these people in Rome notoriously refused to do their job until distressed citizens negotiated with Crassus over the sale of their homes for minimal prices. For ten points, name this profession held by people who put out blazes.", "answer": "<b><u>Firefighter</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Firemen</u></b>; or <b><u>Firewomen</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was given the name \"Big Turtle\" after becoming the adopted son of Chief Blackfish following his capture by the Shawnee. This former Quaker led an expedition to scout the area which became the Wilderness Road. This head of the Transylvania Company founded a namesake \"Borough,\" one of the first colonial settlements west of the Appalachians. The Cumberland Gap was blazed by, for ten points, what pioneer who settled modern Kentucky?", "answer": "Daniel <b><u>Boone</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This actress gave a four-day tour during the Korean War called \"Anything Goes.\" The nation of Egypt unilaterally banned this actress's films due to her conversion to Judaism following her marriage to Arthur Miller. At Madison Square Garden, this actress performed \"Happy Birthday, Mr. President\" for then head of state John F. Kennedy. The film<em> Some Like it</em> <em>Hot</em> features, for ten points, which cultural icon and actress from the mid-20th century?", "answer": "Marilyn <b><u>Monroe</u></b> (accept Norma Jeane <b><u>Mortenson</u></b>; or Norma Jeane <b><u>Baker</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The Barbar Temple in modern Bahrain is dedicated to a god of this domain, the Sumerian deity Enki. Duringearly conversion efforts, Spanish colonists equated the biblical episode of the \"Binding of Isaac\" to instances of child-sacrifice to the Aztec god of this domain, Tlaloc. The citizens of Athens supposedly rejected the gift of a god of this domain, which took the form of a spring. For ten points, name this primary domain ruled by Poseidon.", "answer": "<b><u>Water</u></b> (accept the <b><u>Ocean</u></b>; or the <b><u>Sea</u></b>; accept <b><u>rain</u></b>; prompt on \"rivers\" or \"storms\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "This disease's primary vector of transport was discovered by Paul-Louis Simond [[see-MOHND]] while in Bombay during its \"third\" major breakout. The most prominent symptom of this disease is the inflammation of lymph nodes in the groin, neck, and armpits. This disease is caused by the bacterium<em> Yersinia pestis</em>, and historically spread through black rats carrying fleas aboard merchant vessels. For ten points, name this disease that killed about one third of the European population in a pandemic called the Black Death.", "answer": "<b><u>Bubonic</u></b> Plague (prompt on \"Black Death\" or \"Black Plague\" before mentioned; prompt on \"plague\")", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Treaty of Fort Stanwix set Indian Territory's southern border at this river, settlement near which sparked Lord Dunmore's War. This river was known as the \"River Jordan\" by enslaved people, who often had to cross it to escape North. Fort Pitt was constructed where this river is formed from the Allegheny and Monongahela [[mah-non-gah-HEH-lah]] Rivers. For ten points, name this river that forms the southern border of Indiana and a namesake midwestern state.", "answer": "<b><u>Ohio</u></b> River", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This regime's Admiral of the Fleet was assassinated by royalist Fernand de la Chapelle, who hoped to place Henry VI [[the sixth]] on the throne. As a result of Case Anton, this regime's naval secretary Gabriel Auphan [[oh-FAHN]] scuttled its fleet at Toulon [[too-LOHN]]. This state facilitated \"round-ups,\" like at Vel' d'Hiv [[VEL DEEV]], to deport Jews to Nazi camps. For ten points, name this collaborationist regime of France during World War Two, led by Philippe Petain [[peh-TAHN]].", "answer": "<b><u>Vichy</u></b> France (or R\u00e9gime de <b><u>Vichy</u></b>; accept <b><u>French State</u></b>; or <b><u>\u00c9tat fran\u00e7ais</u></b>; prompt on \"France\" alone; do not accept \"Free French\" or \"Free France\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Near the Westfjords of Iceland, thirty sailors from this region were massacred for being foreigners. In Operation Ogre, the ETA separatist organization, agitating for the freedom of this region, killed Luis Carrero Blanco. The historical Kingdom of Navarre [[nah-VAHR]] was in this region, centered on the city of Pamplona. The city of Bilbao is located in, for ten points, what autonomous region of Northern Spain?", "answer": "<b><u>Basque</u></b> Country (or <b><u>Euskadi</u></b>; or Pa\u00eds <b><u>Vasco</u></b>; accept <b><u>Basque</u></b> Autonomous Community; or <b><u>Euskal</u></b> Autonomia Erkidegoa; or Comunidad Aut\u00f3noma <b><u>Vasca</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The splinter group ISWAP launched an invasion of this organization's headquarters during the Battle of Sambisa [[sam-BEE-sah]] Forest, leading to the death of this group's leader, Abubakar Shekau [[ah-boo-BAH-ker sheh-KOW]], by suicide vest. This organization, whose name usually translates to \"Western Education is Forbidden,\" attempted to scare civilians by kidnapping 200 school girls in Chibok. Al-Qaeda has materially supported, for ten points, which Nigerian terrorist organization?", "answer": "<b><u>Boko Haram</u></b> (accept <b><u>Jam</u><u>\u0101</u><u>'at Ahl as-Sunnah lid-Da'wah wa'l-Jih</u><u>\u0101</u><u>d</u></b>; accept <b><u>Group of the People of Sunnah for Preaching and Jihad</u></b>; accept<b><u> Wil</u><u>\u0101</u><u>yat Garb Ifr</u><u>\u012b</u><u>q</u><u>\u012b</u><u>y</u><u>\u0101</u></b>; accept <b><u>Western Education is Forbidden</u></b> before mentioned; do not accept or prompt on \"Islamic State's West Africa Province\" or \"ISWAP\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A tribe who lives primarily in this region called the Pirah\u00e3 [[pee-RAH-hah]]</u> <u>speak a language that notably lacks words for specific numbers. The Yanomami are</u> <u>(+)</u> another widely-studied native group from this region. The Vale do Javari [[hah-VAH-ree]] is a massive reserve for indigenous peoples in the Brazilian (*) </b>portion of this region. Indigenous rights and territories are threatened in, for ten points, what largest rainforest in the world?", "answer": "<b><u>Amazon</u></b> Rainforest (accept Floresta <b><u>Amaz\u00f4n</u></b>ica; accept Selva <b><u>Amaz\u00f3n</u></b>ica)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Under the flag of truce, this rebellion's leader, James McFarlane, was shot by a</u> <u>rogue soldier, leading to a march on Pittsburgh. This (+)</u> insurrection was caused by a tax meant to allow the federal government to pay off Revolutionary War debts. The greatest domestic crisis of the Washington administration (*)</b> was, for ten points, what Pennsylvania rebellion caused by a tax on alcohol?", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey</u></b> Rebellion (accept \"Revolt\" or \"Insurrection\" for \"Rebellion\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Christopher Marlowe was a member of this figure's counter-cultural circle</u> <u>known as the \"School of Atheism.\" This Governor of Jersey was tried and imprisoned</u> <u>in the Tower of London for (+)</u> his involvement in the Main Plot, an attempt to depose James Stuart. The word \"Croatoan\" was etched in a tree near the lost colony of Roanoke, which (*)</b> was founded by this man. For ten points, name this Elizabethan noble who is the namesake of the capital of North Carolina.", "answer": "Sir Walter <b><u>Raleigh</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this empire, the</u></b><em><b><u> Chaki taklla</u></b></em><b><u> was a foot plow used by farmers due to a lack of</u> <u>large pack animals. This state employed</u></b><em><b><u> chasqui</u></b></em><b><u> [[CHAH-skee]] couriers, who kept</u> <u>record of transactions using the</u></b><em><b><u> quipu</u></b></em><b><u> [[KEE-poo]] knotted-string (+)</u> system. This</b> <b>empire</b> <b>experienced</b> <b>a</b> <b>civil</b> <b>war</b> <b>between</b> <b>Huascar</b> <b>and</b> <b>Atahualpa</b> <b>[[ah-tah-HWAHL-pah]] prior to its conquest by the Spanish. (*)</b> For ten points, name this Andean empire that was conquered in 1533 by Francisco Pizarro.", "answer": "<b><u>Inca</u></b>n Empire (or the <b><u>Inca</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Tawantinsuyu</u></b>; or <b><u>Realm of the Four Parts</u></b>; or <b><u>Four Parts Together</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This archipelago's Bogoslof volcano erupted in 2017, briefly interrupting air</u> <u>traffic between North America and Asia. The Rat Islands, Near Islands, and Fox Islands</u> <u>are (+)</u> part of this archipelago, which was known until 1867 as the Catherine Islands. This group's islands of Kiska and Attu were occupied by Japan during World War Two. Unalaska is the (*)</b> most populous community in, for ten points, what group of islands southwest of the Alaskan Peninsula?", "answer": "<b><u>Aleut</u></b>ian Islands (or <b><u>Aleut</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Aleutic</u></b> Islands; accept <b><u>Catherine</u> </b>Archipelago before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>A composer from this nation dedicated the piece</u></b><em><b><u> Anchor and Star</u></b></em><b><u> to its navy</u> <u>following the outbreak of war with Imperial Germany. This nation's entrance into the</u> <u>Second World War inspired the composition of</u></b><em><b><u> Fanfare for the Common Man</u></b></em><b><u> by Aaron</u> <u>Copland. (+)</u> This nation's native composer John Adams created the piece</b><em><b> On the </b><b>Transmigration of Souls</b></em><b> in the wake of the 9/11 terrorist attacks here. John Philip Sousa composed</b><em><b> Stars and Stripes</b></em><b> (*)</b><em> Forever</em> to serve as a military march for, for ten points, which Western nation?", "answer": "<b><u>United States</u></b> of America (or <b><u>USA</u></b>; prompt on \"America\" alone)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This battle occurred concurrently with Operation St\u00f6sser [[STUH-suh]], which</u> <u>reportedly called for the use of carrier pigeons. During a siege at this battle, one</u> <u>commander responded to a surrender demand by simply replying (+)</u> \"Nuts!\" Also known as the Ardennes Counteroffensive, this battle is considered the last roll of the dice for Adolf Hitler. (*)</b> For ten points, name this World War Two battle which is named for a distinct shape in Allied lines.", "answer": "The Battle of the <b><u>Bulge</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ardennes Counteroffensive</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>It's not Italy, but under King Hassan II, this country's \"Years of Lead\" saw</u> <u>extreme political repression. This country's Alaouite [[ah-LOO-ite]] dynasty took</u> <u>power in the 1600s and includes its ruler since 1999, Mohammad VI [[sixth]]. This (+)</u> country organized the 1975 \"Green March\" to seize land claimed by the Spanish Polisario Front and has ongoing territorial disputes with Ceuta [[SYOO-tuh]] and Melilla [[meh-LEE-yah]], the only Spanish cities on (*)</b> Africa's mainland. For ten points, name this country that occupies most of Western Sahara.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Morocco</u></b> (accept al-Mamlaka al-<b><u>Ma</u><u>\u1e21</u><u>rib</u></b>iyya; or the <b><u>Western</u> <u>Kingdom</u></b>; accept Tageldit n l<b><u>meghrib</u></b>; or Royaume du <b><u>Maroc</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}